Poushkin Society in America Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Poushkin Society in America Records 1931-1955
MSS36707
Poushkin Society in America
3,000 items
8 containers
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Society celebrating poet Aleksandr Sergeevich Puskin. Correspondence, minutes, programs, literary contest essays, clippings, an index to Pushkin's Boris Godunov, photographs, and other records relating chiefly to Pushkin and the formation and history of the society.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Avinoff, Andrey, 1884-1949--Correspondence.; Brasol, Boris, 1885-1963--Correspondence.; Gogolʹ, Nikolaĭ Vasilʹevich, 1809-1852.; Lermontov, Mikhail I︠U︡rʹevich, 1814-1841.; Obolensky, Serge, 1901-1992--Correspondence.; Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich, 1799-1837.; Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich, 1799-1837. Boris Godunov. 1831.; Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1873-1943--Correspondence.; Rostovtzeff, Michael Ivanovitch, 1870-1952--Correspondence.; Sikorsky, Igor Ivan, 1889-1972--Correspondence.; Sorokin, Pitirim Aleksandrovich, 1889-1968--Correspondence.; Vernadsky, George, 1887-1973--Correspondence.
Organizations
Poushkin Society in America.
Subjects
Authors, Russian--Societies, etc.--United States.; Poets, Russian--Societies, etc.--United States.; Russian literature.; Russian poetry.
Provenance
The records of the Poushkin Society in America were given to the Library of Congress in 1956 by Boris Brasol.
Access and Restrictions
The records of Poushkin Society in America are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Poushkin Society in America span the years 1931-1955. The collection chronicles the society's efforts to promote and celebrate the Russian poet Aleksandr Sergeevich Pushkin. The collection is arranged in four series: General Correspondence, Subject File, Printed Matter, and Index to Boris Godunov.
The General Correspondence consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence relating to society events, publications, and other interests. The Subject File includes material relating to anniversary celebrations by the society, which included celebrations for Pushkin, Mikhail Íuévich Lermontov, and Nikolai Vasil'evich Gogol; bylaws, minutes, and other material relating to the history and organization of the society; and photographs. The printed matter, consisting primarily of newsclippings also includes pamphlets and booklets relating to Pushkin and Russian literature. A Russian language index to Pushkin's Boris Godunov comprises the final series.
Correspondents include Audrey Auinoff, Boris Brasol, Serge Obolensky, N.A. Pushkin, Sergei Rachmaninoff, M. I. Rostovťsev, Igor Ivan Sikorsky, Pitirim Aleksandrovich Sorokin, and George Vernadsky.
Arrangement of the Records
This collection is arranged in four series:
General Correspondence, 1934-1955
Subject File, 1934-1955
Printed Matter, 1931-1954
Index to Boris Godunov (in Cyrillic alphabet), undated
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1934-1955 (Box 1-3)
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence relating to the society.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1934-1936, (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1937-1953, (9 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1954-1955, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Subject File, 1934-1955 (Box 3-6)
  Bylaws, minutes, photographs, a notebook, and other material relating to anniversary celebrations by the society and the history and organization of the society.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Administrative, 1934-1939, undated (Box 3)
  - Anniversaries (Box 3)
    - Gogol, Nikolai Vasil'evich, 1951-1952, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - Lermontov, Mikhail Íuévich (Box 4)
      - Contest entries, 1939-1941, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - General, 1939-1941, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (including Pushkin), 1936-1953, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 4, Box 5)
    - Poushkin Society in America (Box 5)
      - General, 1954-1955, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Notebook, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1937, undated (Box 6)
- Printed Matter, 1931-1954 (Box 6)
  Newsclippings, pamphlets, booklets, and other material relating to Pushkin and Russian literature.
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1954, (6 folders) (Box 6)
- Index to Boris Godunov (in Cyrillic alphabet), undated (Box 7-8)
  An index to Pushkin's Boris Godunov.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - A-M (Box 7)
  - H (N)-Я (Box 8)